When we park in a big parking lot,
حين نركن في موقف سيارات كبير،
how do we remember where we parked our car?
كيف نتذكر أين ركننا سيارتنا؟
Here's the problem facing Homer.
هذه المشكلة التي تواجه هومر.
And we're going to try to understand
وسوف نحاول فهم
what's happening in his brain.
ما الذي يحدث في دماغه.
So we'll start with the hippocampus, shown in yellow,
حسنا سنبدأ بالحُصين، الملون بالأصفر،
which is the organ of memory.
والذي هو العضو المسؤول عن الذاكرة.
If you have damage there, like in Alzheimer's,
إن كان لديكم ضرر هنا، مثلما في الزهايمر،
you can't remember things including where you parked your car.
لا يمكنكم تذكر أشياء بما في ذلك أين ركنتم سيارتكم.
It's named after Latin for "seahorse,"
وهو مسمى بذلك نسبة إلى المصطلح اللاتيني ل"فرس البحر"
which it resembles.
والذي يشبهه.
And like the rest of the brain, it's made of neurons.
ومثل بقية الدماغ، فإنه مكون من خلايا عصبية.
So the human brain
وبالتالي الدماغ البشري
has about a hundred billion neurons in it.
لديه حوالي 100 مليار خلية عصبية.
And the neurons communicate with each other
والخلايا العصبية تتواصل مع بعضها البعض
by sending little pulses or spikes of electricity
من خلال إرسال نبضات صغيرة أو تموجات كهربائية
via connections to each other.
من خلال الروابط لبعضها البعض.
The hippocampus is formed of two sheets of cells,
الحُصين مكون من صفيحتين من الخلايا،
which are very densely interconnected.
والتي هي مترابطة بكثافة.
And scientists have begun to understand
والعلماء بدؤوا يفهمون
how spatial memory works
كيف تشتغل الذاكرة الفضائية
by recording from individual neurons
من خلال تسجيل خلايا عصبية مفردة
in rats or mice
في الجرذان أو الفئران
while they forage or explore an environment
وهي تجمع المؤونة أو تستكشف المحيط
looking for food.
بحثا عن الطعام.
So we're going to imagine we're recording from a single neuron
حسنا سنقوم بتخيل أننا نسجل من خلية عصبية واحدة
in the hippocampus of this rat here.
في حُصين هذا الجرذ هنا.
And when it fires a little spike of electricity,
وحين تطلق تموجا من الكهرباء،
there's going to be a red dot and a click.
ستظهر نقطة حمراء وطقطقة.
So what we see
وبالتالي ما نراه
is that this neuron knows
هو أن تلك الخلية العصبية تعرف
whenever the rat has gone into one particular place in its environment.
كلما ذهب الجرذ إلى مكان معين من الفضاء.
And it signals to the rest of the brain
وترسل إشارة إلى باقي الدماغ
by sending a little electrical spike.
من خلال إرسال تموج كهربائي صغير.
So we could show the firing rate of that neuron
وبالتالي أمكننا عرض إطلاق الجرذ للخلية العصبية
as a function of the animal's location.
كدالة لمكان الحيوان.
And if we record from lots of different neurons,
وإن سجلنا الكثير من الخلايا العصبية المختلفة،
we'll see that different neurons fire
سوف نرى أن خلايا عصبية مختلفة تطلق (موجات)
when the animal goes in different parts of its environment,
حين يذهب الحيوان إلى أماكن من مختلفة من فضائه،
like in this square box shown here.
مثلا في هذا الصندوق المربع الذي يظهر هنا.
So together they form a map
وبالتالي (الخلايا) مجتمعة تشكل خريطة
for the rest of the brain,
لبقية الدماغ،
telling the brain continually,
تخبر الدماغ باستمرار،
"Where am I now within my environment?"
"أين أوجد الآن ضمن محيطي؟"
Place cells are also being recorded in humans.
خلايا الأماكن تُسجل حاليا كذلك عند البشر.
So epilepsy patients sometimes need
وهكذا يحتاج مرضى الصرع أحيانا
the electrical activity in their brain monitoring.
إلى أنشطة كهربائية في مراقبة أدمغتهم.
And some of these patients played a video game
وبعض هؤلاء المرضى لعبوا لعبة فيديو
where they drive around a small town.
حيث يقودون في أرجاء مدينة صغيرة.
And place cells in their hippocampi would fire, become active,
وخلايا الأمكنة في حصينهم تطلق (نبضات)، وتصبح نشطة،
start sending electrical impulses
تبدأ في إرسال نبضات كهربائية
whenever they drove through a particular location in that town.
كلما كانوا يقودون خلال مكان معين في تلك المدينة.
So how does a place cell know
وبالتالي كيف تعرف خلية مكانية
where the rat or person is within its environment?
أين يوجد الجرذ أو المرء في محيطه؟
Well these two cells here
حسنا، هاتين الخليتان هنا
show us that the boundaries of the environment
تظهران لنا أن حدود المحيط
are particularly important.
مهمة بشكل خاص.
So the one on the top
وبالتالي تلك في الأعلى
likes to fire sort of midway between the walls
يروق لها أن تطلق نوعا من الطريق الوسط بين الجدران
of the box that their rat's in.
من الصندوق الذي يوجد فيه الجرذ.
And when you expand the box, the firing location expands.
وحين توسع الصندوق، تتسع أماكن الإطلاق (الكهربائي)
The one below likes to fire
الذي في الأسفل يروق له الإطلاق
whenever there's a wall close by to the south.
كلما وجد جدار قريب من جهة الجنوب.
And if you put another wall inside the box,
وحين تضع جدارا آخر داخل الصندوق،
then the cell fires in both place
ثم تطلق الخلية في كلا المكانين
wherever there's a wall to the south
كلما وجد جدار في الجنوب
as the animal explores around in its box.
بالتزامن مع استكشاف الحيوان للصندوق.
So this predicts
وبالتالي هذا يتوقع
that sensing the distances and directions of boundaries around you --
أن تحسس مسافات واتجاهات الحدود حولنا --
extended buildings and so on --
المباني الممتدة وما إلى ذلك --
is particularly important for the hippocampus.
مهم بالخصوص بالنسبة للحصين.
And indeed, on the inputs to the hippocampus,
وفي الواقع، في مدخلات الحصين،
cells are found which project into the hippocampus,
تم إيجاد خلايا تقوم بالإسقاط على الحصين،
which do respond exactly
والذي يتجاوب تماما
to detecting boundaries or edges
مع الكشف عن الحدود والحواف
at particular distances and directions
على مسافات واتجاهات معينة
from the rat or mouse
من الجرذ أو الفأر
as it's exploring around.
وهو يكتشف ما حوله.
So the cell on the left, you can see,
وبالتالي فالخلية على اليسار، يمكن أن تروا،
it fires whenever the animal gets near
تطلق كلما اقترب الحيوان
to a wall or a boundary to the east,
من جدار أو حاجز في اتجاه الشرق
whether it's the edge or the wall of a square box
سواء كان حافة أو جدار لصندوق مربع
or the circular wall of the circular box
أو جدارا دائريا للصندوق الدائري
or even the drop at the edge of a table, which the animals are running around.
أو حتى المنخفض على حافة الطاولة، التي تجري حولها الحيوانات.
And the cell on the right there
والخلية على اليمين هناك
fires whenever there's a boundary to the south,
تطلق كلما وجد حد في الجنوب،
whether it's the drop at the edge of the table or a wall
سواء كان المنخفض على حافة الطاولة أو جدارا
or even the gap between two tables that are pulled apart.
أو حتى الفجوة بين الطاولتين المفروقتين عن بعضهما.
So that's one way in which we think
وبالتالي تلك هي الطريقة التي نعتقد أن
place cells determine where the animal is as it's exploring around.
الخلايا المكانية تستخدمها لتحديد أين يوجد الحيوان وهو يستكشف ما حوله.
We can also test where we think objects are,
يمكننا كذلك أن نفحص أين نعتقد أن الأشياء توجد،
like this goal flag, in simple environments --
مثل راية الهدف، في أوساط بسيطة --
or indeed, where your car would be.
أو في الواقع، أين قد توجد سيارتك.
So we can have people explore an environment
بحيث يمكننا أن نجعل الناس يستكشفون وسطا
and see the location they have to remember.
ونرى المكان الذي عليهم تذكره.
And then, if we put them back in the environment,
ومن ثم، إن وضعناهم مجددا في الوسط،
generally they're quite good at putting a marker down
هم على العموم يجيدون وضع العلامة
where they thought that flag or their car was.
حيث اعتقدوا أن الراية أو سيارتهم كانت.
But on some trials,
لكن في بعض التجارب،
we could change the shape and size of the environment
يمكن أن نغير شكل وحجم الوسط
like we did with the place cell.
كما فعلنا مع الخلية المكانية.
In that case, we can see
في تلك الحالة، يمكننا أن نرى
how where they think the flag had been changes
كيف تغير المكان الذي يعتقدون أن الراية وجدت فيه
as a function of how you change the shape and size of the environment.
كدالة لكيفية تغيير شكل وحجم الوسط.
And what you see, for example,
وما ترونه، على سبيل المثال،
if the flag was where that cross was in a small square environment,
إذا كانت الراية حيث كانت العلامة في وسط مربع صغير،
and then if you ask people where it was,
وثم حين تسأل الناس أين كانت،
but you've made the environment bigger,
لكنك جعلت الوسط أكبر،
where they think the flag had been
حيث يعتقدون أن الراية كانت
stretches out in exactly the same way
يتسع تماما بنفس الطريقة
that the place cell firing stretched out.
التي يتسع بها إطلاق الخلية المكانية.
It's as if you remember where the flag was
إنه كما لو أنك تتذكر أين كانت الراية
by storing the pattern of firing across all of your place cells
من خلال حفظ نمط الإطلاق على امتداد خلاياك المكانية
at that location,
في ذلك المكان،
and then you can get back to that location
وثم يمكنك العودة إلى ذلك المكان
by moving around
من خلال التحرك حول المكان
so that you best match the current pattern of firing of your place cells
بحيث تنطبق أكثر مع النمط الحالي لإطلاق خلاياك المكانية
with that stored pattern.
مع ذلك النمط المحفوظ.
That guides you back to the location that you want to remember.
وذلك يقودك رجوعا إلى المكان الذي تريد تذكره.
But we also know where we are through movement.
لكننا كذلك نعلم أين نحن على امتداد الحركة.
So if we take some outbound path --
وبالتالي إن سلكنا مسارا خارجيا --
perhaps we park and we wander off --
ربما نركن السيارة ونتجول --
we know because our own movements,
نعرف لأن حركاتنا،
which we can integrate over this path
والتي يمكن أن ندمجها على امتداد المسار
roughly what the heading direction is to go back.
تقريبا ما هو اتجاه طريق العودة.
And place cells also get this kind of path integration input
والخلايا المكانية تحصل كذلك على هذا النوع من المدخلات
from a kind of cell called a grid cell.
من نوع من الخلايا تدعى خلايا شبكية.
Now grid cells are found, again,
الآن الخلايا الشبكية يمكن إيجادها، مجددا،
on the inputs to the hippocampus,
في مدخلات الحصين،
and they're a bit like place cells.
وهي نوعا ما مثل الخلايا المكانية.
But now as the rat explores around,
لكن الآن والجرذ يستكشف ما حوله،
each individual cell fires
كل خلية مكانية مفردة تطلق
in a whole array of different locations
في نسق كامل من الأماكن المختلفة
which are laid out across the environment
الموضوعة على امتداد الوسط
in an amazingly regular triangular grid.
في شبكة مثلثية منتظمة بشكل مدهش.
And if you record from several grid cells --
وإن سجلت من عدة خلايا شبكية --
shown here in different colors --
معروضة هنا بألوان مختلفة --
each one has a grid-like firing pattern across the environment,
كل واحدة لديها نمط إطلاق شبه شبكي على امتداد الوسط،
and each cell's grid-like firing pattern is shifted slightly
وكل نمط إطلاق شبه شبكي للخلية يحول قليلا
relative to the other cells.
بالنسبة للخلايا الأخرى.
So the red one fires on this grid
وبالتالي الحمراء تطلق على هذه الشبكة
and the green one on this one and the blue on on this one.
والخضراء على هذه والزرقاء على هذه.
So together, it's as if the rat
وبالتالي مجتمعة، وكأن الجرذ
can put a virtual grid of firing locations
يمكنه وضع شبكة من أماكن إطلاق
across its environment --
على امتداد وسطه --
a bit like the latitude and longitude lines that you'd find on a map,
نوعا ما مثل خطوط الطول والعرض التي قد تجدها في خريطة،
but using triangles.
لكن باستخدام مثلثات.
And as it moves around,
وكما تتحرك حول المكان،
the electrical activity can pass
يمكن للأنشطة الكهربائية المرور
from one of these cells to the next cell
من إحدى هاته الخلايا للخلية للموالية
to keep track of where it is,
لتتبع أين توجد،
so that it can use its own movements
بحيث يمكنها استخدام حركاتها الخاصة
to know where it is in its environment.
لمعرفة أين توجد في وسطها.
Do people have grid cells?
هل يتوفر الناس على خلايا شبكية؟
Well because all of the grid-like firing patterns
حسنا بسبب أن كل أنماط الإطلاق الشبه شبكية
have the same axes of symmetry,
لديها نفس محاور التماثل،
the same orientations of grid, shown in orange here,
نفس توجه الشبكة، معروض باللون البرتقالي هنا،
it means that the net activity
يعني ذلك أن النشاط الصافي
of all of the grid cells in a particular part of the brain
لكل الخلايا الشبكية في جزء معين من الدماغ
should change
يجب أن يتغير
according to whether we're running along these six directions
حسب ما إذا كنا نجري على طول هذه الاتجاهات الستة
or running along one of the six directions in between.
أو نجري على طول واحدة من الاتجاهات الستة بينها.
So we can put people in an MRI scanner
بحيث يمكننا أن نضع الناس في جهاز التصوير بالرنين المغناطيسي
and have them do a little video game
ونجعلهم يقومون بلعبة فيديو بسيطة
like the one I showed you
مثل التي أريتكم إياها
and look for this signal.
ونبحث عن الإشارة.
And indeed, you do see it in the human entorhinal cortex,
وبالفعل، فإنك تراها في القشرة الشمسية للإنسان،
which is the same part of the brain that you see grid cells in rats.
والذي هي نفس الجزء من الدماغ حيث ترى الخلايا الشبكية في الجرذان.
So back to Homer.
إذن لنعد إلى هومر.
He's probably remembering where his car was
هو على الأرجح يتذكر أين كانت سيارته
in terms of the distances and directions
من حيث المسافات والاتجاهات
to extended buildings and boundaries
للبنايات الممتدة والحدود
around the location where he parked.
حول المكان الذي ركن فيه سيارته.
And that would be represented
وهذا يمكن أن يتمثل
by the firing of boundary-detecting cells.
من خلال إطلاق خلايا استشعار الحدود.
He's also remembering the path he took out of the car park,
هو كذلك يتذكر المسار الذي سلكه خروجا من موقف السيارات،
which would be represented in the firing of grid cells.
والذي قد يتمثل في إطلاق الخلايا الشبكية.
Now both of these kinds of cells
الآن كلا نوعي الخلايا
can make the place cells fire.
يمكنه جعل الخلايا المكانية تطلق.
And he can return to the location where he parked
ويمكنه العودة إلى المكان الذي ركن فيه
by moving so as to find where it is
بالتحرك بحيث يجد أين
that best matches the firing pattern
يطابق أكثر نمط الإطلاق
of the place cells in his brain currently
للخلايا المكانية في دماغه حاليا
with the stored pattern where he parked his car.
مع النمط المحفوظ حيث ركن سيارته.
And that guides him back to that location
وهذا يقوده رجوعا إلى ذلك المكان
irrespective of visual cues
بغض النظر عن الإشارات البصرية
like whether his car's actually there.
مثل ما إذا كانت سيارته توجد بالفعل هناك.
Maybe it's been towed.
ربما قد تم قطرها.
But he knows where it was, so he knows to go and get it.
لكنه يعرف أين كانت، وبالتالي يعرف أن يذهب ويأخذها.
So beyond spatial memory,
وبالتالي ما وراء الذاكرة الفضائية،
if we look for this grid-like firing pattern
إن بحثنا عن نمط الإطلاق هذا الشبه شبكي
throughout the whole brain,
في جميع أرجاء الدماغ،
we see it in a whole series of locations
نراه في سلسلة كاملة من الأماكن
which are always active
والتي هي دائما نشطة
when we do all kinds of autobiographical memory tasks,
حين نقوم بكل أنواع مهام السيرة الذاتية في الذاكرة،
like remembering the last time you went to a wedding, for example.
مثل تذكر آخر مرة ذهبت إلى عرس، على سبيل المثال،
So it may be that the neural mechanisms
وبالتالي ربما الآليات العصبية
for representing the space around us
لعرض الفضاء من حولنا
are also used for generating visual imagery
تستخدم كذلك في توليد صور مرئية
so that we can recreate the spatial scene, at least,
بحيث يمكننا إعادة إنشاء المشهد المكاني، على الأقل،
of the events that have happened to us when we want to imagine them.
للأحداث التي وقعت لنا حين نريد تخيلها.
So if this was happening,
وبالتالي إن كان هذا يحدث،
your memories could start by place cells activating each other
ذكرياتكم قد تبدأ من خلال تفعيل الخلايا المكانية لبعضها البعض
via these dense interconnections
من خلال هذه الروابط الكثيفة
and then reactivating boundary cells
ثم إعادة تفعيل الخلايا الحدودية
to create the spatial structure
لإنشاء البنية الفضائية
of the scene around your viewpoint.
للمشهد حول مرآك.
And grid cells could move this viewpoint through that space.
والخلايا الشبكية تستطيع تحريك هذا المرآى على امتداد ذلك الفضاء.
Another kind of cell, head direction cells,
نوع آخر من الخلايا، خلايا الاتجاه،
which I didn't mention yet,
والتي لم أذكرها بعد،
they fire like a compass according to which way you're facing.
تطلق مثل بوصلة حسب الطريق الذي تواجهه.
They could define the viewing direction
تستطيع تعريف اتجاه النظر
from which you want to generate an image for your visual imagery,
الذي تريد من خلاله توليد صورة للصور المرئية،
so you can imagine what happened when you were at this wedding, for example.
بحيث يمكنك تخيل ما حدث حين كنت في هذا العرس، على سبيل المثال،
So this is just one example
وبالتالي هذا مثال واحد فقط
of a new era really
لعصر جديد بالفعل
in cognitive neuroscience
في علم الأعصاب الإدراكي
where we're beginning to understand
حيث نبدأ في استيعاب
psychological processes
العمليات النفسية
like how you remember or imagine or even think
مثل كيف تتذكر أو تتخيل أو حتى تفكر
in terms of the actions
من حيث أفعال
of the billions of individual neurons that make up our brains.
ملايير الخلايا العصبية المفردة التي تشكل أدمغتنا.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)